<sect1 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="plugins-development">
    <title>For Developers</title>
	<info>
	</info>
	<sect2 xml:id="plugins-development-basic">
	        <title>Basic concept</title>
            <para>
				DDS offers a possibility for external developers to make their own RMS plug-ins.
			</para>
			<para>
				Conceptually, each RMS plug-in is just an executable, which uses a simple DDS plug-in API and is able to deploy and execute a DDS worker package on a corresponding RMS.
            </para>
			<para>
				The following is a basic workflow:
	  	      <itemizedlist>
	  	                <listitem>
	  	                <para>
							User requests to deploy DDS agents or a given RMS using the <link linkend="dds-submit">dds-submit --rms XXXX</link> command. Where XXXX is the name of the plug-in user wants to use.
	  	                </para>
	  	                </listitem>
	  	                <listitem>
	  	                <para>
							DDS commander server receives the request, looks for a suitable plug-in (associated with the XXXX name) and starts it. Plug-in has 2 minutes to connect back to commander to receive exact details about the submit request.
	  	                </para>
	  	                </listitem>
	  	                <listitem>
	  	                <para>
							Once plug-in is started it should contact with the DDS commander server using DDS API, receive details and deploy agents on a given RMS. That's so far it.
	  	                </para>
	  	                </listitem>
	  	      </itemizedlist>
			</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 xml:id="plugins-development-requirements">
	        <title>Requirements</title>
			<itemizedlist>
			          <listitem>
			          <para>
						DDS requires each plug-in to have the name according to the following format: <filename>dds-submit-<replaceable>XXXX</replaceable></filename>, where XXXX is the name of the plug-in (or name of RMS it wraps). All lower case characters.
			          </para>
			          </listitem>
			          <listitem>
			          <para>
						A DDS plug-in (executable) and all related files must be sandboxed in a dedicated folder: <filename class='directory'>$DDS_LOCATION/plugins/dds-submit-XXXX/</filename>.
			          </para>
			          </listitem>
			          <listitem>
			          <para>
						  A DDS plug-in should take only one command line argument <cmdsynopsis><arg>--id <replaceable>arg</replaceable></arg></cmdsynopsis>
						  DDS will call the plug-in with this command line argument and will provide a unique Id, which the plug-in must use when ever it communicates with DDS commander server (see &quot;plug-in-id&quot; in the <link linkend="plugins-development-api">API</link> section for more info).
			          </para>
			          </listitem>
			          <listitem>
			          <para>
						  Plug-ins are responsible to remove all own temporary files on exit. DDS doesn't take ownership of any file create by plug-ins.
			          </para>
			          </listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 xml:id="plugins-development-api">
	        <title>API</title>
            <para>
				The <link xl:href="http://dds.gsi.de/doc/api-docs/DDS/html/classdds_1_1intercom__api_1_1CRMSPluginProtocol.html">dds::intercom_api::CRMSPluginProtocol</link> is a wrapper class for plug-in/"DDD commander server" communication.
            </para>

			<para>
				Once started and ready the plug-in should subscribe on the "submit and "message" command from the DDS commander server.
<programlisting language="c++">
CRMSPluginProtocol prot(&quot;plug-in-id&quot;);

prot.onSubmit([](const SSubmit&amp; _submit) {
	// Implement submit related functionality here.
	
	// After submit has completed call stop() function.
	prot.stop();
});
	
	
prot.onMessage([](const SMessage&amp; _message) {
	// Message from commander received.
	// Implement related functionality here.
});
</programlisting>
onSubmit will deliver to the plugin-in the actual request <link xl:href="http://dds.gsi.de/doc/api-docs/DDS/html/structdds_1_1intercom__api_1_1SSubmit.html">dds::intercom_api::SSubmit</link>. It can contain either a configuration file (format of the file is plug-in depended) or simply a number of agents to deploy. But it will always contain the path to the worker package, which plug-in is supposed to deploy on RMS and execute.
Additionally developers can use a DDS command line tools to find out the location of the worker package: <link linkend="dds-user-defaults">dds-user-defaults --wrkscript</link>. This is especially useful when plug-ins use shell scripts.
			</para>

			<para>
				Once ready the plug-in let's give a hit to DDS commander that we are online and ready for a job:
<programlisting language="c++">
// This must be the first call to let DDS commander know that we are online.
prot.sendInit();
</programlisting>
After that commander will form a submit request and will send it back to the plug-in.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				DDS commander and plug-in communication is asynchronies, therefore either you are responsible to keep the "prot" object alive or simply use:
<programlisting language="c++">
// Stop here and wait for notifications from commander.
prot.wait();
</programlisting>
which will block the main thread until one of the condition is true:
<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
          <para>
			10 minutes timeout,
          </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
          <para>
			Failed connection to DDS commander or disconnection from DDS commander,
          </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
          <para>
			Explicit call of the stop() function
          </para>
          </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
			</para>
			
			<para>
				Once connected you can use <function>proto.sendMessage</function> to send messages. Those messages will be displayed to user while he/she waits on <link linkend="dds-submit">dds-submit</link> command.
				Be advised, that once commander receives the error message it will forward it to the user and close connection as it means a failed submission.
			</para>

			<para>
				We strongly recommend to protect CRMSPluginProtocol calls in a try/catch block, as all methods can throw std::exceptions:
<programlisting language="c++">
try {
	CRMSPluginProtocol prot(&quot;plug-in-id&quot;);
	
	prot.onSubmit([](const SSubmit&amp; _submit) {
		// Implement submit related functionality here.

		// report something back to a user
		proto.sendMessage(dds::EMsgSeverity::info, "Text of the info message");

		// After submit has completed call stop() function.
		prot.stop();
	});
	
	
	prot.onMessage([](const SMessage&amp; _message) {
		// Message from commander received.
		// Implement related functionality here.
	});
	
	prot.onRequirement([](const SRequirement&amp; _requirement) {
		// Implement functionality related to requirements here.
	});
										   
	// This must be the first call to let DDS commander know that we are online.
	prot.sendInit();
										   
	// Wait for notifications from commander.
	prot.wait();
	} catch (exception&amp; _e) {
		// Report error to DDS commander
		proto.sendMessage(dds::EMsgSeverity::error, e.what());
	}
</programlisting>

			</para>
	</sect2>
	
</sect1>
